<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An English answer to the Scotch speech. Shewing the intollerableness of tolleration in matters of religion. And converting each argument in that speech to its most reasonable, genuine, and proper use, and each paragraph into an argument against its author. / By W.K., a lover of loyalty, truth and tranquility ; and one who accounts it a dignity, as well as duty, to be an obedient son of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>W. K., fl. 1668</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K23B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981538</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981538</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2824:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An English answer to the Scotch speech. Shewing the intollerableness of tolleration in matters of religion. And converting each argument in that speech to its most reasonable, genuine, and proper use, and each paragraph into an argument against its author. / By W.K., a lover of loyalty, truth and tranquility ; and one who accounts it a dignity, as well as duty, to be an obedient son of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>W. K., fl. 1668</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Edward Man, and are to be sold at his Shop at the Sign of the Swan near York-house in the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpiece; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ENGLISH ANSVVER TO THE Scotch Speech, Shewing the <hi>Intollerableneſs</hi> of TOLLERATION In Matters of RELIGION. AND Converting each Argument in that Speech to its moſt Reaſonable, Genuine and Proper Uſe; and each Paragraph into an Argument againſt its <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. K.</hi> A Lover of Loyalty, Truth and Tranquility; and one who Accounts it a Dignity, as well as Duty, to be an Obedient Son of the CHURCH of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Edward Man,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Sign of the <hi>Swan</hi> near <hi>York-Houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1668.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180262:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180262:2"/>
            <head>AN <hi>ENGLISH</hi> ANSWER TO THE <hi>SCOTCH SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Urely, Sir, I ſhould much offend you, ſhould I not conclude you of the ſame Mind with the Author of this your Re-printed <hi>Oration:</hi> For that were to deale too plainly with you, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare you Guilty of what thoſe of your Gang are too much attainted, <hi>viz.</hi> The Watermans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practice, of Rowing one way, and looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. But there was ſure ſome extraordinary impulſe active in your <hi>Orator;</hi> (For all things are Miraculous that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to your Party) and we now are bound to believe him a Prophet, ſince your very thoughts and words were by way of Anticipation, or Praediction delivered to King <hi>James the Fifth</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> a hundred years ſince. I ſhall therefore let the Author ſleep with his Fathers, and make no reflections upon the departed; for, in that juncture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and conſidering the temper of that Nation, the Advice might
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180262:3"/>
then be Prudent and Politick. But becauſe, if <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s <hi>Metemſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſis</hi> be true, you are poſſeſſed with his <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Genius; give me leave to animadvert a little upon it as your Bratt, and none of his. I cannot conclude you any great Politician, or deſerving the title of a Mr. of Reaſon, and conſequently unfit to document a Prince, becauſe you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to diſtinguiſh, between Nation and Nation; Party and Party; nay, the very ſame Party, as they may lie under different circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>viz.</hi> between Presbyterified-Separatiſts painting their Tenets with Plauſible Pretences, and the Varniſh of Sanctity; waſhing their Opinions in Milk and Butter: and the ſame Schiſmaticks, as diſplaying their Sentiments with greateſt confidence, ſounding them forth with Trumpet and Drum; and involving a Kingdom (the Genuine conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of their Tolleration) in Warr, and Blood. To deale ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with you, I muſt begg your pardon; if I take you for one of a Linſewoolſy-temper; a Party per pale Puritan, and Papiſt. For I pretend not to Divine the Authors meaning (though it may be the Author and Printer are both the ſame;) For this Stile was not in thoſe dayes, or in that Nation currant and intelligable, with reference to the Affaires then on Foot: but yours, in Publiſhing it at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent juncto; And to me it is plain, that when you talke of two Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, you then plead for the Papiſt; and when of Separatiſts, you are the Non-conformiſts-Champion. And, it is not amiſs that you make the diſcovery, for Experience as well as <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor</hi> gives us to underſtand, that there is no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> between them: And we may juſtly fear that Popery will not be long baniſhed, if a Tolleration be granted. That I preſume is the thing you all aime at, let your Pamphlets be never ſo little to the purpoſe, and your Practice a cleere Confutation of the Propoſition: But the evill of this hath been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently evinced by a more Learned Pen; and my deſign now is to Anſwer a Fool according to his Folly, leaſt he be wiſe in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: Therefore not daring to direct my Lines to the Supreme, I ſhall Levell them at Your Self, and only deſire you to peruſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Periods of your Speech a little converted into other Senſe, and leave the Readers to Judge which ſtands to moſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the many Curſes that God in theſe laſt dayes hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon this our Native Land, this is not the leaſt; that he hath been pleaſed permiſſively to open the Bottomleſs Pit, and hath fulfilled St. <hi>Iohns Revelation, Chap.</hi> the 9th. in ſuffering many Locuſts to cover this our Earth; who, having the Faces of Men, and the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180262:3"/>
of Saints, yet have Stings in their Tailes, and have hurt this our Land many times five Moneths, <hi>viz.</hi> That brood of Sectaries, who have once darkened the Sun of Regall Majeſty, and now endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour again the ſecond time by their Infectious breath to Smoak it into an Eclipſe. And amongſt the many Bleſſings the Subjects of this Kingdom have injoyed under the Gracious Government of our Dear and Dread Sovereign, this is not the leaſt conducing to the Weale of this Nation. That the Honourable Houſe of Commons, have had a Gracious Liberty, and the Religious boldneſs to open their Mindes, and Declare their Opinions, <hi>viz.</hi> That Schiſmatical Perſons are not fit objects of Favour; and that it doth not conſiſt with the Grandeur of Royall Majeſty to bend to them, who will not bend to it; and who do not only confidently bend, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently break all its Sanctions.</p>
            <p>And if ever there was a time thus ſtrictly to determine, it is this: and the inſolency of the Factious doth importunately require it. For, in matters of Advice and Conſultation, we cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes follow what is moſt Reaſonable, nor what Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention in ſome reſpects may require; but what Neceſſity drives us unto, and what is moſt convenient for the preſent time, and what may be fairly accompliſhed and effected. For though we grant that which we need not, <hi>viz.</hi> That in a Spirit of meekneſs the Errors of the Weak are to be tollerated in the Re-printers ſenſe; Yet it being moſt apparent, that they, who pretend to be ſo, are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not weak: And ſince, not only Reaſon and Scripture <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, but dear-bought Experience teaches us, that that Tolleration no whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes to the prevention of Diſſentions; but that ſufferance enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Inſolence of the Party<hi>:</hi> So that after a grant of 19 Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they will be ſo impudent as to Rebell, Should they be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the 20th? And ſince it is apparent, that to enfringe an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Law for the pleaſure of a Few, would be a Sovereign way to make Lawes cheap, Authority contemptible, and Sectaries proud, who ſwell too much already. It cannot be deny'd, but that that Moderation and meekneſs, that forbearance and condeſcention, which might be exerciſed towards ſome particular Perſons, cannot without apparent danger be granted generally to the Party; and that the very Safety of the <hi>STATE</hi> denies ſuch a Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The Eſtate of the Kingdom is much troubled with divers Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180262:4"/>
concerning Religion: and it is to be wiſhed that the only true Religion were in the hearts of every Subject<hi>:</hi> But ſince diverſity of Opinions of Religion, and Hereſies, are the very puniſhment of God Almighty upon Men for their horrible Vices, Roaring Sins, and hypocriticall Deluſions: And when Men forſake his fear, and true obedience, God abandoneth them to their own Opinions and Fantaſies in Religion, and giveth them over to believe lies; Out of which ariſe Partialities, Factions, Diviſions, Strife, Inteſtine Diſcords, which burſt forth into Civill Warr, and in ſhort time bring Kings and Kingdomes to their laſt Periods, Therefore, that matters may not ariſe to ſuch a heighth of inſolency, and that the Seditious <hi>Spirit</hi> of 40 and 48, which did then imbrue the Land in Blood, may not again be encouraged by Connivance and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, without diſſembling my thoughts, I cannot but averr; That the preſervation of the Lawes Eccleſiaſticall and Civill, Inviolable and Entire, and a due care to quicken and Execute them; will be the beſt way to preſerve the Peace, and promote the Unity of this Land and Nation.</p>
            <p>I hold it the deſire of none but Perſons Jeſuitted, to Wiſh for the Free-Exerciſe of two Religions: for, under the pretence and ſhadow of them, the common Peace of the Subject will be torn in peices. And certainly your Magiſteriall Doctor his Interrogation is altogether deſtitute of wiſdom and truth<hi>:</hi> For (though like a ſimple ſophiſter you ſeem to deny it) Wiſdom may deviſe a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty for Separatiſts (whoſe Principles do not lead them directly to Rebellion) that is neither Death nor Baniſhment (for theſe two are not immediate oppoſites, and therefore the Propoſition is pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and fallacious) there being a Medium between them, <hi>viz,</hi> a Pecuniary Mulct, or lighter Corporal Puniſhments. But it is the Trick of theſe Scriblers, like their Father the Devil, <hi>Fortiter Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniari,</hi> and to Exaſperate the People, by telling them what Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties they muſt expect, and what Torments are Decreed; hoping thereby to excite them to Rebellion, under the Specious Pretence of Liberty, and Self-preſervation. But though I muſt freely ſay, as to the Promoters of a Religion differing in Fundamentalls from the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and introducing another Supreme Head of the Church, that thoſe two Puniſhments are moſt fit for them, and deſerved by them; yet as to thoſe who only differ in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Ceremonies from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180262:4"/>
way not as yet thought on by our addle-headed Reprinter; <hi>viz.</hi> to let them be tollerated as to living, converſing, and injoying liberty amongſt us; but let them be fined for the neglect of Divine Service, and their verboſe Teachers diſcountenanced and ſilenced; and this I take to be a way different farr from that which is here propoſed. But theſe men love to ſcare the people into ſedition, and to make them believe that death is threatned, and many evils invented which were never thought of by any but themſelves. And whereas this opinion of the conveniences of inflicting penalties for Non-conformity to cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, may ſeem to interfere with that rule of <hi>Quod tibi ſieri non vis, &amp;c.</hi> It will eaſily be rejoyned, though that Axiome always is of force in commutative juſtice, yet I preſume it is not ſo in that we call diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive, which comprehends the affairs of Superiours with Inferiours: becauſe inferiours are not competent judges in the caſe, till the tables be turn'd and themſelves ſuppoſed the power offended, and then they have determined the caſe to our hands; even then when their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was altogether unlawful, and no other then a notorious uſurpation and divelliſh Tyranny.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as a Prince begins upon the inſolencie and impudence of ſome obſtinate diſſenters to comply with the Traitors, and condeſcend to their Petitions: He gives them an incouragement the more to plague and peſter him with Petitions, Declarations, Remonſtrances, &amp;c. And ſhall find (which I pray God avert from this Nation) that they will never leave inching and asking, till they have juſtled, and puſht him out of his Throne. And here again we have the Presbyterian knack of lying: for as ſoon as the Prince denies to them who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved death, an intereſt in his peculiar favour and kindneſs; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently exclaim that he ſpoils, baniſhes, kills, and burns his people for matters abſtract from ſenſe and altogether Spiritual; when as in truth and reality he onely frowns on them, and checks them for diſobedient contumacy to his Laws and Edicts, and their clancular endeavour to ſet Church and State into uproar and combuſtion, rather than ſubmit to what they acknowledge indifferent.</p>
            <p>It is a very great and malicious errour in you (Maſter reprinter) to affirm the diſcountenancing of Regecides, or at leaſt the ringleaders to that barbarous inhumanity, a perſecuting of them for an opinion of Piety, and for matters of Faith: And unleſs you take faith in a very looſe ſenſe you cannot here be excuſed from being the Papiſts advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, (who are latitudinarians in Faith in a contrary ſenſe to them that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180262:5"/>
are ſo in conformity: for whilſt thoſe will do ſomething, theſe will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all things) whoſe cauſe (I dare ſay) was never promoted by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, but cauſing all diſſenters from it to ſuffer: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance of their doctrine with mens carnal intereſts being a cogent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to the Libertine to embrace it; and therefore your argument here being very inſignificant deſerves no further anſwer. But if by matters of faith, you mean ceremonies of Religion, and the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of men about things indifferent, you then broach a Lye for the intereſt of the Presbyter, for you never yet knew any condemned to death for any ſuch diſſent, nor any number gained to the factious party by the obſtinate ſufferings of a vain-glorious Pyrgopollinices. But it is the frequent practice of theſe ſeditious ſcriblers to amuſe men with brags of their Proſelytes, and boaſts of their number; hoping thereby to affright their Superiours into a complyance with their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Now how it can conſiſt with the prudence of a Parliament to be Hectored and Hufft into a yielding to the factious, whoſe very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and notions ſtrike at Supremacy, I do not underſtand.</p>
            <p>It would ſurely be no great errour of State to endeavour the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting of turbulent and implacable Spirits. For though I queſtion not, but that the men you plead for, are inveterate enemies to their native Countrey, yet there is certainly ſome probable hopes that theſe artiſts of ſedition, might do us a courteſie in making uproares abroad as they have done at home. Neither is this (Good Sir) an extravagant fancy: for your Beloved Sir <hi>H. Vane</hi> that Baronet of Babel; had in ſome few months almoſt ſet the whole Plantation of Conciſtorian <hi>New England</hi> into as bad a combuſtion as you did this of Old. But however, ſuppoſe we ſhould fail of our hopes in this: yet ſure it is far better (if their enmity be implacable) to have our enemies abroad then to have them at home, a Swelling in the Arm, or an exterior Boil, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo dangerous, as an impoſtume or an ulcer neer the Heart, or in the Kidneys.</p>
            <p>I cannot but think (Sir) you have taken up Arms, and profeſs open hoſtility to ſound reaſon: In that you tell us here in a ſettled Kingdom, where the intereſts of the Church are intricately interwoven with thoſe of the State, that Religion is not to be preached by arms, that is in truth (if you would a little lay aſide your Tragical Language) that Schiſmaticks are not by penalties to be reſtrained, and bring in the firſt Primitive days to avouch it. As if there were no difference between a Church eſtabliſhing, and one eſtabliſhed: and that becauſe they were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180262:5"/>
deprived of the Magiſtrates countenance, and conſequently could not proceed in that Method; that therefore it is unlawful for Chriſtian Kings to puniſh with the ſword temporal, thoſe who violate their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, ſurely this is no judicious arguing. And again (as if there were no difference to be made between Religion it ſelf, and the adjuncts thereof) to argue that becauſe the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel was not impoſed by force on the infidels; that therefore obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to an acknowledged legal Authority, ought not to be enforced upon Chriſtian Profeſſours, though the things to be ſubmitted to are matters of order and decency, is ſo poor a ſhift that it deſerves not a line more to confute it: We ſhall readily grant you, that you never knew any arms taken up by True Proteſtants (For I muſt tell you I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not the Separatiſts ſo) for the matter of Religion, for when the Epiſcopal party went of late into the Field, it was to defend their Soveraign, and alſo themſelves: But theſe deteſters of Wars (becauſe their horns are ſhort) they were the men that made the abuſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and fear of Superſtition; their pretence to invade the King and his Subjects. And we now (I hope) ſhall not need to enterprize that difficulty you ſpeak of, and put our ſelves in arms againſt Sectaries, as ſuch. But if theſe men (as it is natural to them) prove as great traitors in deeds as they are already in words, I hope the enterprize will not be thought unlawful; for ſure he's neither a good <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> nor a good Chriſtian, who will not endeavour their ſuppreſſion. Little need is there of arms to force men to be Hypocrites, when hypocriſie is ſo ready to force men into arms; And I cannot in charity judge him any other then a hypocrite, who under pretence of Religion arms his tongue with reproaches: and whoſe fingers itch at a ſword, and all this againſt his undoubted Soveraign. I muſt agree with you herein, that fire and iron cannot work upon mens ſouls: but yet let me tell you, they have been found more effectual then love and pity; for theſe men you are concern'd for, will break ſooner then bend, and are not ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious as to be moved with mercy. And therefore (good Sir) whilſt we love, and in our excellent Litany deſire their converſion, and pray for their perſons, give us leave to withſtand and oppoſe their obſtinate errours.</p>
            <p>The Will muſt be acknowledged to be free from neceſſitation, and coaction, but yet not ſo free but that it may be attracted by motives, and perſwaſives; by rational arguments, and judicious reaſonings into a complyance with what before it could not ſubmit to; and it is every
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180262:6"/>
mans duty to endeavour to have his underſtanding ſo rightly informed, that his will which follows the dictates and repreſentations of that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er faculty may be complyant and ſequacious to its dictates. But now if in ſtead of this, men ſuffer their wills to uſurp the thrones of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and are reſolved to believe only what they liſt (and the trite Proverb tells us it is an eaſie matter thus to believe) and love to make to themſelves a creed and goſpel out of their own notions, and to frame it according to their own fancies, intereſts and paſſions, who can pity theſe men, if we endeavour to reclaim the ſtubbornneſs of their wills by enacting penalties for their wilfulneſs. I wiſh heartily it were not too true, that there are ſome amongſt us who are ſo addicted to their own fancies, that they reſolve to give a Supremacy to their Wills, and to have and obey no other <hi>Ceſar;</hi> and that tell us this is the God that is to be obeyed rather then man. Sure then, though the power of the Prince be eſpecially over the bodies of men; yet becauſe the body hath ſome influence upon the Soul, and the Soul alſo acts in many things by the body: and eſpecially becauſe it ordinarily appears, that money is the life of theſe mens lives, and there is nothing comes in competition with it, but the vogue of the people, and a great repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; It may not be unreaſonable to puniſh them in their muck and money, for the maliciouſneſs of their minds. True it is, theſe men are members of the body Politick: but ſuch as a Sore-leg is to the body natural, which if it feſters, rankles, gangrens, <hi>Enſe recidendum ne pars ſincera trahatur:</hi> I mean not this in the ſtrict and literal ſenſe: for I love not <hi>Draco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> laws that are writ in bloud; but my meaning is, an old Sore is not to be excuſed from ſharp corroſives; becauſe the part aggrieved is a member of the body, but the ſmarting coſtick may well be uſed in hope of a Cure.</p>
            <p>A nobler way and a gentler connivance hath been uſed with theſe men, then they ever deſerved; Penal laws take no cogniſance of their clancular Preachments, provided there be not above five beſides the family: And our Gratious Soveraign hath for this twelve Months laſt paſt, very much born with their tumultuous Conventicles; But what is the effect of all this Lenity, but an ungrateful impudency and open railery againſt King and Parliament; Though the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act was never yet executed, yet are theſe Unthankful perſons ſo little ſenſeable of the Kings Indulgence to them; that they fear not to aſſert that they do not apprehend it any product of Lenity, but rather the effect of a miraculous Providence, which hath ſtopt and barr'd the mouth of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180262:6"/>
Lion. Thus they fear not to ſpeak evil of dignities; and ſpread evil reports of the Lord's Anointed. But can Tolleration be thought the way to Union, as you ſeem to intimate? or is poiſon to be antidoted by keeping it in the Stomack? Surely, Sir, both Propoſitions are equally probable. Since therefore Lenity will not avail to cure them, Severity muſt be endured by them, and adminiſtred to them, for who can help what will away?</p>
            <p>It is falſe, irrational, and abſurd to affirm, that diverſity of Religions is not deſtructive to Society, and a bar to the civil Converſation of men. Sure, Sir, you are a great ſtranger in Iſrael, if you know not what Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, a meer difference in opinion, hath rendred ſome <hi>Oliverians</hi> to the Loyal party: And as great a ſtranger are you to the Tempers of men, and the Wiles of Satan, if you have not obſerved, that ſuch a diverſity is the Author of feuds, and bitter animoſities; and that Two Religions like <hi>Ceſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> will be always at Daggers drawing for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy; the one not enduring any Superiour, the other hating the thoughts of an equal. For every man being ſo far his own Paraſite, as to flatter himſelf into a belief that the truth is on his ſide; will take all occaſions to aſſert, and promote it; and to malign them who ſeem to oppoſe it. And then nothing will be ſo common as to caſt reproaches upon the higheſt Authority that ſhall diſſent from them, and to averre ſuch Tolleration a ſilent conceſſion of the goodneſs of their cauſe; for ſuch impudent concluſions are not ſeldom extorted from gracious premiſes.</p>
            <p>And why, I pray, may not our almoſt infinite, and moſt pragmatical ſects be as kind and good natured as the Moncks are, who content themſelves with, and ſubmit themſelves to the Orders and Rules of their Holy Father the Pope, acknowledging and embracing him as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, though impoſing Novelties as Articles of Faith, and have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good reaſon to yield onely unto him a paſſive, but no active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: I am ſure our diſſenters of the Claſſical Order, have much more reaſon to acquieſs in the Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions of our Church, then they of theirs: becauſe our Holy Mother the Church hath declared to her children in her Rubrick of Ceremonies, that they are indifferent in themſelves, and are onely impoſed for the ſake of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and decency; and makes nothing an Article of faith which God hath not. So that here lies the difference between theſe two parties, they, I mean the various orders in the Romiſh Church, are lull'd into a repoſe by the drowſie rockings of a blind obedience, and our Separatiſts
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180262:7"/>
here would hurry us into confuſion, by their impudent ſtickling for a perverſe diſobedience; they ſin by eaſie ſubmiſſion, but theſe ſin more by the Witchcraft of Rebellion. But ſince you know, whoſe property it is to be queſtioniſt, and I apprehend this Paragraph a weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable one, I ſhall onely ſay that therefore theſe Separatiſts and Papiſts cannot be ſuffered; becauſe we have found by an experience, that hath been the price of Royal bloud, that Lenity and Kindneſs will not reduce theſe men to the right Government: that they cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to practice againſt the politick Laws and Conſtitutions of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and therefore it is not fit they be tollerated in the State.</p>
            <p>The Murthers, Slaughters, Battels, Maſſacres, which not long ſince aroſe, and were promoted amongſt us, were the unhappy conſequents of putting power into the hands of theſe cruel Separatiſts, and a too great condeſcention unto them. Opportunity not onely makes a thief, but alſo diſcovers the diſpoſitions of men; And if we are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind (which is the worſt obſcurity) we cannot but ſee they have given us a ſufficient Comment upon their Natures, how inclined they are to fleſh themſelves with bloud and ſlaughter, to ravage and roar like Famiſhed Lions, though they thereby ſacrifice their Souls to the infernal powers. Sure then this ſhould be a cogent argument to clip their Claws, becauſe an unjuſt and imprudent Tolleration would open a gate to all this impiety. For who ſees not, that they are ſo far from repentance, that they are traverſing over again their old ſteps, and want nothing but a <hi>Rump Parliament</hi> to ſet them a gog. Good reaſon then hath this our Prudent Parliament to look to themſelves, their Laws, and the Kingdom; and provide manacles for theſe <hi>Orlando Furioſoes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſeeking Liberty of Religion theſe men ſeek to believe any thing that may whimſically come, or, by a cunning Jeſuit, be ſubtilly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated into their brains. And under the pretence of Religion, and the exerciſing of it, according to the firſt Chriſtians inſtitution, they will neither ſerve God, nor obey the Laws under which they are born.</p>
            <p>That Maxime ſo often repeated amongſt the Church-men of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath not (in their ſenſe) been ever executed upon the Separatiſts of <hi>England;</hi> At leaſt not upon them as Separatiſts, and Diſſenters from us in Religion, but as they have been guilty of ſedition and treaſon, which is the Lacquey attendant upon the zealous Separatiſt. And this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that where Hereticks are countenanced, and the ſeditious encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, there neither the power of the Prince ſhall be preſerved, nor yet the benefit of the Common people long maintained. The next
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180262:7"/>
way to bring in infidelity, is to ſuffer men to believe what they liſt, for by that means they will at laſt believe nothing at all.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Kings are obliged to advance the glory of God, and the Salvation of their Subjects, by taking care that the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be orthodoxly preached, and duly adminiſtrated to them. And though it is plain, that you here ſquint at the revenue of the Church; as your great eye-ſore, yet give me leave to tell you that double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>i. e.</hi> extraordinary maintenance as well as countenance is to be given to them, who by his Majeſty are called to watch over the Souls of his Subjects. It is queſtionleſs the Magiſtrates duty to uphold and encourage moſt ſingularly the Biſhops, that take care that the Word be preached without ſophiſtication and the higgling Knavery of whining Oratory and extemporary non-ſenſe: That ſee that the people be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in their duty both to God and the King, which though never ſo often joyned together in Scripture, ſhall be ſure to be ſeparated either directly, or implicitely by theſe Hectors for Schiſme. Now this you call governing the Kingdom by the intereſts of Prieſts, a ſhrewd ſign that your deſire is to have a nation of Atheiſts. I heartily wiſh that rule you ſeem to harp on: viz. <hi>Quicquid propter Deum fit, aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter fit,</hi> were duly obſerved by this phariſaical generation; for then I am ſure whilſt they religiouſly plead for the obſervation of the Sabbath, they would not wickedly forget the fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Now then ſince this Vice cannot be Tollerated but by the ruine of the State; and ſince there is a greater obligation, and neceſſity of Law to puniſh Hereticks, and obſtinately ſeditious Separatiſts, than Fornicators, and other ſuch ſcandalous Livers; becauſe they are more immediately deſtructive of civil Society, and the peace of a Nation than theſe are (though it is true, For theſe things the wrath of God comes on the children of diſobedience.) It cannot be thought that they are perſons to be indulged, being ſo neet of Kind to the Vipor. For how hath the beams of favour hardned their dirty diſpoſitions, emboldening them to ſpit their poiſon even at the King himſelf, and to talk treaſon with a familiar confidence; which that it may not be brought into act, it concerns the Magiſtrate not to be hufft out of their Severity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:180262:8"/>
Theſe Men (I know) would willingly be thought to be of the ſame nature and condition of which we are: They pretend to Worſhip the ſame God as we do, but forget he hath ſaid, Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evill of the Ruler of the People. And whereas <hi>Michael</hi> the <hi>Arch-Angel</hi> brought not a Railing Accuſation againſt the Diſputing Devil, theſe men ſtudy nothing but Slanders and Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms againſt the Fathers of the Church. And in truth, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Gayety of their Pretences, the Differences between them and us, will be found ſo vaſt, that nothing but their Conformity, or their Suppreſſion can ſecure our Tranquility. I know none that deſires to have them Proſecuted with Fire and Sword, that Smells Rank of the Schiſmatical Humour, who have from their Succeſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to perſwade us, That God was in their bitter Diviſions and Alenation of Affections; in their Raging Flames of Mutiny and Sedition; in the Tempeſts, and Turbulent Whirl-wind of a Spirit of Contradiction; and not in the Gentle Breathings after Peace and Concord: It being no leſs then Sequeſtration to Teach the People Allegiance. This is the Sport their Fingers now Itch at; But we would fain perſwade them to Love and Amity, by Chalking out unto them the good Old-Way<hi>:</hi> we would give them Light, but they ſhut their eyes; we endeavour to cut off the Scales, and they cry out we Kill them. In Muſicall Inſtruments if a String jarr, and be out of Tune, and will not by any Arts and gentle means be veered about to a Concord, but ſnaps and flyes in the very face of the Muſician, it is broke off, thrown aſide, and a new one put in its room. Let not us therefore be ſo cruel to our ſelves, as to doat on thoſe Serpents, who have already ſtung us almoſt to death, and of whoſe dolorous wounds we are not as yet recovered.</p>
            <p>Let theſe Men therefore be guided by reaſon, and reſt ſatisfied in the Decrees of the Council of the Nation<hi>:</hi> For, as they have been ſufficiently proved Erroneous, ſo they have too apparently proved themſelves Seditious and Treacherous. That the Opinions they Maintain are contrary to the Principles and Practiſe of the Antient Church, is clear as the day: only to inſtance in that which the time of the Year mindes me of. They deny it a duty to Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Feſtival of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> which never but one Light-headed-Aerius aſſerted before them<hi>:</hi> otherwiſe this their Tenet would have been Condemned by a Lawful Council; but what need that, ſince Saint <hi>Auſt.</hi> tells us, that the Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſcention
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180262:8"/>
of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Coming of the <hi>Holy Ghost, Toto terrarum orbe univerſaria ſolennitate celebrantur.</hi> And you ſhall find that the four firſt Councils did not diſpute the Matter, but the Manner, <hi>viz.</hi> The true Time of its Obſervation<hi>:</hi> Let their Worſhip of God be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that of the Firſt Age, you ſhall find a difference too great to be Indulged.</p>
            <p>You do well <hi>(Sir)</hi> to Compare your Devotoes to the Refractory <hi>Jewes,</hi> and had I a mind to exceed a ſheet of Paper, I could ſhow you a large Analogie between them<hi>:</hi> But I ſhall only tell you, that if <hi>Rome</hi> had been ſo Havockt and Injured by the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> there; as we have, by them of the <hi>Conciſion</hi> here, they would have again verifyed that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> and have burnt up all the Synagogues of God in their Land. But theſe Men are worſe Incendiaries then the cruell <hi>Iewes:</hi> for though they have had Inſtructions from a free and Lawfull Counſil; yet they abandon all thoughts of Re-union and Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and think it a diſparagment to their Names, to forſake their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p>That which ſome of them believe, <hi>viz.</hi> The Doctrine of <hi>Enthuſiaſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c. is falſe and evill, and that in many Grand-Articles of our Chriſtian Faith<hi>:</hi> The Faith of ſome others, though right as to the main, in reſpect of Doctrine; yet is ſo inveterately bent againſt the Churches Diſcipline, that their ignorant Zeale inevitably excites them to Confront both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Authority; and to reduce Church-Matters to their Penitential-ſtool, and Imperious Conſiſtory, And if it be no offence to judge of the Tree by its fruits, we may ſay, without any violence to Chriſtian Charity, that they are in this reſpect defective in good, and have eſpouſed and obtained an habit of evil: They are not therefore Condemned before they are Judged, nor yet Judged before they are heard; for the ſound of Trumpets with which they Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumed People to Battel, and their Curſings of the People after the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <hi>Meroz,</hi> becauſe they would not Fight againſt the Lords Annointed, are ſufficient Proclamations of their Opinions to the World. And we have all the reaſon in the World to Conclude, That it is their Paſſion and Perverſeneſs; their Pride and Peeviſhneſs; and not their Religion that troubles the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:180262:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THink not (Gentle Reader) that I live to rake in Ranckled-Soares, it's not my Inclination, but their preſumption that hath produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced theſe Lines, which I hope, conſidering that they follow the preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions of another Mans Fancy, may be excuſed from the imputation of ſevere Railery: Since I have but laid the Bratt at the Right Door, and given them their own in their own Language. And I cannot but hope theſe few Lines may alſo ſerve to enervate the Miſ-applied Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments contained in a Letter</hi> To a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for the Promotion of Liberty of Conſcience. <hi>Becauſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>nor the</hi> Primitive-Chriſtians <hi>ever Experimented (as we have done) thoſe Tollerated by them, ſo deſtructive to their</hi> Policy, <hi>as theſe men have been to ours: If they had, there would have been proviſions made for their Suppreſſion and Extirpation. And though the</hi> Epiſtler <hi>paſſes it over as a thing not worth noting; yet to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men, it will be of moment to think, that the Totall deſtruction of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Nation was the immediate conſequent of their numerous Sects.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:180262:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
